# Matthew Haffner

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR · DEPARTMENT OF GEOGRAPHY AND ANTHROPOLOGY · UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN - EAU CLAIRE

Phillips Science Hall 257, 101 Roosevelt Blvd, Eau Claire, Wisconsin 54701

Academic interests: Spatial Data Science, Quantitative Methods, Digital Geographies, Urban Geography

# Professional Employment \_\_\_\_\_

<b>Assistant Professor</b> , Dept. of Geography and Anthropology, University of Wisconsin - Eau Claire	2018+	
<b>Graduate Research Assistant</b> , Dept. of Geography, Oklahoma State University	2016-2018	
<b>Programmer</b> , Dept. of Plant and Soil Sciences, Oklahoma State University	2015	
Graduate Teaching Assistant, Dept. of Geography, Oklahoma State University		
Transportation Intern, Association of Central Oklahoma Governments		

#### Education

#### **Oklahoma State University**

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY IN GEOGRAPHY

Stillwater, Oklahoma Aug. 2014 - May 2018

- Dissertation: Assessing the validity of location-based social media in the study of spatial processes
- Comprehensive exam areas: GIScience, Urban Geography, the GeoWeb
- Co-advisors: G. Allen Finchum, Adam J. Mathews

#### **Oklahoma State University**

MASTER OF SCIENCE IN GEOGRAPHY

Aug. 2012 - July 2014

- Thesis: Measuring social interaction potential in Oklahoma City and Tulsa
- Advisor: Hongbo Yu

#### **Pittsburg State University**

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN SECONDARY EDUCATION

• Majors: Geography and Mathematics

Pittsburg, Kansas

Stillwater, Oklahoma

Aug. 2007 - May 2012

## **Publications** \_\_\_\_

#### PEER-REVIEWED JOURNAL ARTICLES

- Ochsner, T., E. Linde, and **M. Haffner**. Mesoscale soil moisture patterns revealed using a sparse in situ network and regression kriging. *Water Resources Research*. Accepted **2019**.
- Fekete, E. and **M. Haffner**. Twitter and academic geography: A look at #AAG2018. *Professional Geographer*. Accepted **2019**.
- **Haffner, M.** A place-based analysis of #BlackLivesMatter and counter-protest content on Twitter. *GeoJournal*: 1-24. **2018**.
- **Haffner, M.** A spatial analysis of non-English Twitter activity in Houston, TX. *Transactions in GIS* 22(4): 913-929. https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/tgis.12335. **2018**.

- **Haffner, M.**, A. J. Mathews., E. Fekete, and G. A. Finchum. Location-based social media behavior and perception: Views of university students. *Geographical Review* 108(2):203-224. doi:10.1111/gere.12250. **2017**.
- Mathews, A. J., **M. Haffner**, and E. Ellis. GIS-based modeling of tornado siren sound propagation: Refining spatial extent and coverage estimations. *International Journal of Disaster Risk Reduction* 23:36-44. doi:10.1016/j.ijdrr.2017.04.004. **2017**.

## PEER-REVIEWED JOURNAL ARTICLES (UNDER REVIEW)

• **Haffner, M.** and J. C. Comer. An interactive point pattern analysis web application and teaching exercise. *Journal of Geography in Higher Education. Submitted Feb. 2019.* 

#### BOOK CHAPTERS

• **Haffner, M.** Twitter. In *Handbook on Geographies of the Internet*, B. Warf (ed.). Cheltenahm, UK: Edward Elgar Publishing Limited. **2019.** 

#### MAPS

• **Haffner, M.** Location of Greenwood Historic District within Tulsa's contemporary food desert. In *Resilience, Environmental Justice, and the City.* Eds. B. H. Caniglia, M. Vallee, and B. Frank. pp. 84. **2017.** 

## **Professional Conference Presentations**

- **Haffner, M.\*** A place-based analysis of #BlackLivesMatter and counter-protest content on Twitter. *American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting.* Washington, D.C. Paper presentation. April **2019**.
- Haffner, M.\* and J. C. Comer. An interactive point pattern analysis web application and teaching exercise. West Lakes Division of the American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting. La Crosse, Wisconsin. Poster presentation. November 2018.
- Comer, J. C.\* and **M. Haffner** An interactive point pattern analysis web application and teaching exercise. Southwest American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting. Manhattan, Kansas. Paper presentation. October **2018**.
- **Haffner, M.\*** A spatial analysis of non-English Twitter activity in Houston, Texas. *American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting.* New Orleans, Louisiana. Paper presentation. April **2018**.
- Finchum, G. A.\* and **M. Haffner** How good is Twitter data: Comparing phone usage patterns using social media vs. calculated home location. *American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting*. New Orleans, Louisiana. Poster presentation. April **2018**.
- **Haffner, M.\***, A. J. Mathews, E. Fekete, and G. A. Finchum. Location-based social media behavior and perception: Views of university students. *Southwest American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting*. Huntsville, Texas. Paper presentation. November **2017**.
- Haffner, M.\* The development of shp2nosql: Command line tools for spatial data and NoSQL databases. American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting. Boston, Massachusetts. Paper presentation. April 2017.

- Haffner, M.\*, A. J. Mathews., and E. Ellis. GIS-based modeling of tornado siren sound propagation in Stillwater, Oklahoma. *Southwest American Association of Geographers Annual Meeting. Denton, Texas.* Poster presentation. November **2016**.
- **Haffner, M.\*** and A. J. Mathews. A multi-dimensional topology for crowd-sourced geographic information. NSF Workshop on Geospatial Data Science in the Era of Big Data and CyberGIS. Urbana, Illinois. Paper presentation. July **2016**.
- G. A. Finchum\*, **M. Haffner**, A. J. Mathews, and E. Fekete. Analyzing smartphone usage patterns at colleges with strong gender differences using social media. *Association of American Geographers Annual Meeting*. San Francisco, California. Poster presentation. April **2016**.
- **Haffner, M.\*** Conquering big spatial data: Towards a new philosophy in geographic information science. *Oklahoma State University Research Symposium*. Poster presentation. February **2016**.
- Ochsner, T. E.\*, J. Dong, **M. Haffner**, A. Patrignani, J. C. Patton. Developing an operational system for daily 800-m resolution soil moisture estimates across Oklahoma. *American Geophysical Union Fall Meeting*. San Francisco, California. Paper presentation. December **2015**.
- Patton, J. C.\*, T. E. Ochsner, A. Patrignani, J. Dong, **M. Haffner**. Towards a high resolution soil moisture map of Oklahoma. *American Society of Agronomy, Crop Science Society of America, and Soil Science Society of America Annual Meeting.* Minnesota. Poster presentation. November **2015**.
- **Haffner, M.\***, H. Yu. Measuring social interaction potential in Oklahoma City and Tulsa. *Association of American Geographers Annual Meeting*. Chicago, Illinois. Paper presentation. April **2015.**
- Finchum, G. A.\*, **M. Haffner**. Using Twitter data to analyze mobile device usage patterns in urban areas. *Association of American Geographers Annual Meeting*. Chicago, Illinois. Poster presentation. April **2015**.
- **Haffner, M.\*** Using ArcGIS, Python, and R to measure social interaction potential in Tulsa and Oklahoma City. *Oklahoma South Central Arc User Group Meeting*. Moore, Oklahoma. Technical presentation. September **2014**.
- **Haffner, M.\*** Measuring social interaction potential in Tulsa and Oklahoma City: A case study. *Oklahoma State University Research Symposium.* Stillwater, Oklahoma. Paper presentation. April **2014**.

# **Teaching Experience**

COURSES TAUGHT AS INSTRUCTOR OF RECORD

#### **University of Wisconsin - Eau Claire**

- **GEOG-435** Geographic Information Systems III
- **GEOG-370** *Quantitative Methods in Geography*
- **GEOG-337** Geographic Information Systems II
- **GEOG-335** *Geographic Information Systems I* (online)
- **GEOG-111** Human Geography

Eau Claire, Wisconsin June 2018 - present

<sup>\*</sup> Presenting author

#### **Oklahoma State University**

- **GEOG-1113** Introduction to Cultural Geography (lecture)
- **GEOG-1114** *Introduction to Physical Geography* (lecture)
- **GEOG-1114** Introduction to Physical Geography (laboratory)

## **Neosho County Community College**

• MATH-112 Intermediate Algebra

Pittsburg, Kansas Aug. 2011 - Dec. 2011

Stillwater, Oklahoma Aug. 2012 - Dec. 2015

COURSES TAUGHT AS TEMPORARY INSTRUCTOR

#### **Oklahoma State University**

- **GEOG-4383** Introduction to GIS Programming
- **GEOG-3333** Spatial Analysis
- **GEOG-3123** Urban Geography
- **GEOG-2344** Digital Tools for Environmental Exploration
- **GEOG-5343** Advanced GIS: Resource Management Applications

## St. Mary's Colgan High School

- Algebra II (as student teacher)
- Geometry (as student teacher)
- Algebra III (as substitute)
- Calculus (as substitute)

# Stillwater, Oklahoma

Multiple dates

Pittsburg, Kansas Jan. 2011 - May. 2011

# Invited Lectures & Workshops \_\_\_\_\_

- GIS Programming with R (half-day workshop). *Wisconsin Land Information Association Annual Conference*. Appleton, Wisconsin. February **2019**.
- GIS Programming with R (half-day workshop). *Minnesota GIS/LIS Consortium Annual Conference*. St. Cloud, Minnesota. Forthcoming October **2019**.
- Maintaining graduate student life. In *GEOG-5001 Professional Development in Geography.* Oklahoma State University. November **2017**, November **2016**.
- Big data, spatial data science, and volunteered geographic information. In *GEOG-2344 Digital Tools for Environmental Exploration*. Oklahoma State University. September **2017**.
- High performance computing in the social sciences. In *MATH-2910 High Performance Computing.* Oklahoma State University. March **2016**.
- The emergence of urban segregation in the United States. In *GEOG-1113 Introduction to Cultural Geography.* Oklahoma State University. March **2016**.
- GIS programming with PostgreSQL and PostGIS. In *GEOG-4383 Introduction to GIS Programming*. Oklahoma State University. March **2016**.
- Volunteered geographic information, Twitter, and big data. In *GEOG-2344 Digital Tools for Environmental Exploration*. Oklahoma State University. January **2016**, November **2015**.

## **Honors & Awards**.

2019	Summer Research Experiences for Undergraduates	Office of Research and Sponsored Programs,
2019	Grant (\$4600)	UWEC
2017	Norris Conference Travel Scholarship (\$550)	Department of Geography, OSU
2017	Jerry Croft Award in Geography Education (\$1500)	Department of Geography, OSU
2016	Norris Conference Travel Scholarship (\$350)	Department of Geography, OSU
2016	Spring Featured Researcher	High Performance Computing Center, OSU
2015	Research Materials Grant (\$200)	GPSGA, OSU
2015	Most Outstanding First Year PhD Student (\$2000)	Department of Geography, OSU
2015	Susan Shaull Medal for Excellence in Teaching (\$500)	Department of Geography, OSU
2015	Top Tier Graduate Fellowship (\$7500)	Graduate College, OSU
2014	SCAUG Regional Scholarship (\$1500)	South Central Arc User Group
2014	Norris Conference Travel Scholarship (\$500)	Department of Geography, OSU
2013	OKSCAUG Scholarship (\$500)	Oklahoma South Central Arc User Group
2013	Three Minute Thesis Competition Finalist	Graduate College, OSU
2013	Most Outstanding First Year Master's Student (\$1000)	Department of Geography, OSU

# **Professional Memberships**

American Geographical SocietyApr. 2017 - PresentAmerican Association of GeographersNov. 2014 - PresentGamma Theta Upsilon (Geography Honor Society)May 2013 - PresentOSU Forum of Geography Graduate StudentsAug. 2012 - May 2018Fellowship of Christian Graduate StudentsAug. 2013 - May 2015

# **Professional & University Service \_**

- Manuscript reviewer. Professional Geographer (2018, 2019), Geographical Review (2018), International Journal of Applied Geospatial Research (2018).
- Search committee member. Critical nature society geographer position. University of Wisconsin Eau Claire. September December 2018.
- Alternate Member. OSU Student University Technology Services Fee Committee (UTSF). Oklahoma State University. November 2017 present.
- **Secretary**. *Gamma Theta Upsilon (Geography Honor Society)*. Oklahoma State University. August **2017** present.
- **President**. Forum of Geography Graduate Students. Oklahoma State University. August **2016** February **2018**.
- **Co-organizer**. Forum of Geography Graduate Students invited colloquium presentations. Stillwater, Oklahoma. Department of Geography Colloquia. August **2016** present.
- **Co-organizer**. Open source software in geography: Theories, developments, and pathways toward openness. AAG Annual Meeting. Boston, Massachusetts. Paper Session. April **2017**.
- Co-organizer. Open source software in geography: Theories, developments, and pathways toward openness. AAG Annual Meeting. Boston, Massachusetts. Panel Session. April 2017.

- **Co-organizer**. *Securing positions in academia*. Forum of Geography Graduate Students Special Sessions. Stillwater, Oklahoma. Three Part Lecture Series. January **2017**.
- **President**. OSU Fellowship of Christian Graduate Students. Oklahoma State University. August **2013** May **2015**.
- Treasurer. Forum of Geography Graduate Students. Oklahoma State University. August 2012 July 2013.

## Technical Skills

**GIS** R (various libraries), PostGIS, QGIS, MATLAB Mapping Toolbox, ArcGIS Web GIS OpenLayers, Leaflet, GeoServer **Databases/NoSQL systems** ElasticSearch, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, MS SQL Server R, Python, Bash, Emacs Lisp, LaTeX, MATLAB, SQL, C#, HTML, CSS, SAS Languages **Shells** Fish, Zsh, Bash, Eshell **Operating systems** Manjaro, Debian, CentOS, Raspbian, Ubuntu, OS X, Windows **Web Frameworks** Shiny, Hugo, Jekyll, Microsoft .NET Emacs (Spacemacs), Vim, Git, Docker, RStudio, Microsoft Visual Studio **Tools Presentation software** remark.js, reveal.js, LibreOffice Impress, MS PowerPoint Certifications Base SAS Programming for SAS 9 **Graphics editing** Inkscape, Adobe Illustrator **Miscellaneous** RStudio Server, Amazon Web Services, Linode, High Performance Computing

# Software Projects & Consulting \_\_\_\_\_

#### SOFTWARE

Lead developer	Webmap Toolkit: Reproducible tools for geographic teaching and research, Independent project	https://gitlab.com/mhaffner/webmap- toolkit
Sole developer	ispat: Interactive spatial analysis tool, Independent project	https://geohaff.com/ispat
Sole developer	shp2nosql: Command line tools for spatial data and NoSQL systems, Independent project	https://github.com/mhaffner/shp2nosql
Lead developer	Database maintenance and enhancement project, State Historic Preservation Office of Oklahoma	http://nr2_shpo.okstate.edu
Programmer	Soil Moisture Mapping Project, Department of Plant and Soil Sciences, Oklahoma State University	http://soilmoisture.okstate.edu

#### **CONSULTING CLIENTS**

State Historic Preservation Office of Oklahoma City

Ministry of Natural Resources, Kurdistan Regional Government

2018 - present
2017